Ser we start
so last time I uh could not finish all
the kind of materials for the attention
uh so I will uh finish this part and
then we'll move to
CTC
um thank
so
the Monday lecture I was explaining
about the how Transformer uh the change
the kind of the performance uh in speech
recogition and then uh
the uh it's actually not the end of the
the competition uh after that the Google
proposed the uh the architecture called
conformer so I will first explain this
the conformer and the recently the our
group actually also proposed the the
work called Branch former so we will
also explain it so first um coner yeah
it's there are lot of the the something
former so conformer is one of them but
it's actually quite strong and widely
used in speech processing originally
proposed in speech recognition and then
now it's actually used in the menu of
the speech processing
applications conform actually has a the
quite kind of a uh important schemes to
capture the uh the two the information
uh which is very kind of appropriate for
speech modeling one is the global
information so what kind of a Global
Information uh the uh one is Global
Information and uh the other is the
local information and what kind of uh
the global information you can imagine
from the speech we we have to
capture local would be like a pH or some
kind of a other information that is
changing quite kind of the laidly right
Global Information in speech what would
be yeah speaker
information uh anything else
yeah emotion topic semantic syntactic
information which is quite important
actually so uh of course the primary I
would say important part is local
because we have to understand you know
what the
sound is kind of pronunciated but the
global is another kind of important part
so this is not only for speech
recognition the TTS speak uh the speaker
uh cognition speech summarization speech
translation all kind of spe speech
application this the combination of the
local and the global uh is quite
important and then confir is try to make
use of Boss Global Information can be
captured by a self attention which as
you might remember it actually has the
almost All Passes uh to kind of capture
the uh the the the old frames in
sentence and so on right and the uh
local information uh the can be captured
by any other models but the the
comilation new network is actually good
at this so uh conform actually try to
kind of combine this local and Global
information by using a different model
architecture and this is the originally
proposed in the AR transor but this the
the architecture itself is quite kind of
the powerful and can be apply to the
other architecture including the
attention based ASR and the
CDC okay so let's check the the
conformer uh the
architecture uh which is actually the
the extension of the
Transformer so this is just a review of
the Transformer architecture which is
that especially in the encoder we using
the the M self attention uh the feeld
neural network
resid connection position embedding and
CNN down sampling and so on that we kind
of studied last time right and the this
block is actually repeated several times
like a 12 areas or 18 dayas and so on
this block is actually extended I'm not
sure people can check it but actually
this part is almost identical
there is the the different kind of
blocks layers here one is the the
compostion layer and the other is a Fed
for neuron Network layer so basically uh
yeah that's a kind of a combination of
what we know but this combination was
turned out to be very important very
effective especially this compolation
part is again you know taking the local
uh the uh the information U and then
they try to kind
are the important speech information
there are several minor difference like
relative coding and additionally having
a p NE Network here so this is also
called macaron kind of how they say the
the uh the the pushing the the marar
like architecture in the FI Bo new
network so these kind of a three uh the
the uh extension of the uh the from the
Transformer so it's not very big changes
right just you know adding some kind of
existing known the architecture and then
making it as a one big block by the way
the the question in general which one is
having a more parameters in this block
and this
block it can be obvious but of course
right side right actually that the the
this
Fe part actually increase the model
parameters quite a lot so the conformer
generally have a twice
more parameters than the uh the
Transformer so this is also another
reason but anyway with the the conformer
uh the extension we usually have a very
good the performance
Improvement and then given this kind of
approaches our group also actually
studied the some kind of alternative to
the conformer which we call it branch
forer and this is the basically same uh
the the
concept uh that we try to use both
Global local architecture but instead of
uh the combining this
cascader we actually try to use the the
uh the global and local the architecture
in the kind of parallel manner Branch
man and then we actually call this
approach Branch former which is actually
the here in
the the maret self attention can capture
the the the global uh information and
the local part is actually combined by
the the the neural network and
compolation of uh neural network and
then we are the intent to design this
architecture because having a kind of
neural network to be a cascad the
combining would becomes kind of a uh the
neural network architecture itself very
deep right this one is actually from
here to here it is obvious that it is
very deep right although this has a kind
of several kind of the the the residual
connection to kind of mitigate this
issue but still this is very deep and
it's actually turns out that the coner
is a little bit more difficult to
optimize than the Transformer but once
we find a very good optimization hyper
parameters comform is working very well
so we want to kind of avoid this issue
and then I came up with this kind of the
branch architecture and it actually
turns out to be quite kind of powerful
and also the training optimization is
very stable so this Branch for decently
also the extended to deal with the
fusion part here e Branch for is
actually getting quite good performance
and many actually systems are us
starting to using this the the E Branch
for by the way this Branch for is the
proposed by the Ean there the sit one of
the TA
yeah okay so with this kind of Branch
for we actually could get their
reasonable performance so we have shown
some kind of competition uh with the the
giant the companies right and then uh
this is actually the wi the branch forer
so the from until the again you know
until the Google getting the spec
augment the this the LI speech bench
mark is around 8% after spec augment
that we are kind of in the phase of
fighting the this kind of a number in
the around 5% confir is actually quite a
big changes
but the Ean tra is actually the the
improve the performance this is one of
the first result that the the out
performs conform the based on the uh the
new architecture so it doesn't use any
external data and so same kind of a
comparison but the branch home is
actually reaching the best performance
currently Al now that we have several
other architecture that are proposed but
e Branch for is regarding as one of the
best performance architecture in speech
equation okay so uh the now that the I
will move to several kind of discussions
uh that given uh today's uh uh today and
the Monday's sectes so first uh
Transformer versus uh the uh
lsdm we already have our uh the we
already have our uh the the good kind of
improvement in the blsd
uh the Transformer from BM but I
actually
observed the this change I actually
experienced this change I'm sure several
most of the people here already you know
after the transform error right but I am
actually experienced the bsdm error and
then a Transformer so the I can actually
mention some of my personal real
experience about
it actually my experience are that if we
do similar effort blsm is actually
getting similar performance to
Transformer this for speech equation
tasks however the the most difficult
part in B St is that
paralyzation and the one network
actually takes the the three times f it
depend on the number of parameters but
the disable uh amount of parameters and
the if we compare the B St and the uh
Transformer so it's actually takes the
the three times
faster this actually changing the many
things because we can wait we can
actually chune the hyper parameter
optimization hyper parameter uh and so
on uh this kind of a effort is the quite
kind of important also as I mentioned
the model averaging is very important
and the model averaging is what's not
very well working in the BM because of
the kind of lstm the parameter Dynamic
is very different and sometimes
averaging is a HHO but a Transformer is
mostly based on the feed for the neural
network and we can safely the taking the
model aaging so due to that uh we
actually get the quite the good the
performance uh based on the Transformer
that is actually my
experience um it can be an uh the the
nowadays you know obvious what people
may not care so much about
VM uh uh but the uh still VM is actually
quite powerful and the several
application we are using it but the
difference will be the
polarization and after the and before
the Transformer I also changed my mind
uh before that I was actually thinking
that we do not try to tune the
parameters op optimizers as much as POS
possible because it is painful right
instead you know try to kind of more
focusing on the architecture and so on
but after the Transformer we always have
to chune the hyper parameter
optimization hyper parameter so this
actually change of my mind and before
that I didn't usually kind of ask the
people why I didn't do by myself to
chune so much uh so uh this kind of the
uh the information uh that is changing
my
mind and then uh the so this is another
thing some again without tuning we are
not sure uh your kind of new
architecture is really kind of useful or
not so please do not give give up you
know with some kind of bad result uh
without the tuning the uh the uh
optimization hyper parameter it's it's
additional step but other
uh we couldn't really kind of utilize
our new models and so on so this is also
one kind of a the suggestion so but it
is difficult because which mean that we
need to have a the search of the
optimization hyper parameter and then I
find it the the branch for also
originally that we need to have several
tuning and then finally we get the kind
of better performance not perform yeah
that's the Ean can I mention many of the
kind of stories about
it okay so next uh the I didn't talk
about the uh language model at all
because I mentioned that you know
attention based Sr including the
language model effect
right however uh this is actually one
the interesting difference with the H
based
approaches which is at least this kind
of a pure
formulation we cannot train the
model uh only with the text data in the
hmm based approaches it that equation is
complicated but we can split the
language model part and acostic model
part right and please remember language
model part there's no observation which
means that we can train the model with
large amount of text Data p is more data
only text data and text and speech data
air
data of course T only data right which
has tons of data resources so uh
attention based ASL it actually doesn't
have a pure language model effect and
then if we try to incorporate it we have
to kind of a train the both pair data or
some kind of the uh the the adhoc ways
to uh the combine the language model
score which is uh we call Shadow Fusion
by the way the shadow here means that
there are some more kind of a tip
integration uh like kind of a combin the
language model inside the neural network
of the attention based as and then the
fine tune or something which is people
call Deep fusion and this one is Shadow
Fusion because there's such no such kind
of integration part but this uh approach
is very simple we just multiply them but
it's can have a kind of scaling issue
over the probability in this cases we
usually have a scaling parameter here
and then by controlling them we can
actually reduce the effect of the
language model or we can increase the
effect of the language model and so on
so this uh approach
is quite widely used however compared
with the the agent based approaches
there is no theoretical justification
this is just geometric mean and actually
you know the counting the the uh the W
twice this is usually cannot be obtained
from the our kind of map decision Theory
so this is actually ad hoc
approximation or uh the uh the we may
also uh the regard it again
geometrically mean or something like
that so it is not theoretically well
motivated but it's quite widely used
by the way uh this actually
approximation has an issue this means
that we actually have a language model
effect
twice and this is actually sometimes
harmful and then there are lot of kind
of studies to actually try to remove the
effect of the language model especially
in the attention side we don't want to
kind of double count the language model
effect so some people actually try to
kind of subtract the language model
effect in the encod decod part
and then try to kind of purely using the
shadow Fusion language model so this the
technique is called residual language
model and so on this is a little bit
Advanced to topic but this approach
comes from the fact that this actually
uh way is not theoretically
founded founded so we need some kind of
we this is based on some approximation
and we need some adjustment and so on
but this the resid the language model
subtraction is really important and many
of the kind of the speech
recognizer the uh product by Google is
actually based on this approaches so
this means that this sh Fusion is
something
wrong okay uh and then last part and
this is actually also very important
concept so I want to explain this is not
only for the uh the the attention even
AR trans this problem
happens it's that the teacher
foring so uh remember that the we
actually using this kind of
factorization form right and then we can
train the model based on this
factorization
form and then we have a history here
right
during training we know the history we
know the kind of entire history right so
we can just use
them however during inference during
being such can we use the gr Tru history
of course
not we don't because we don't know that
the what is gr right so that's why we
are doing a speech so so there is a big
mismatch during the training the
inference and so on and the many of
actually attention based encod decoda
theoretically there is not so many
approximation right there's no
conditional Independence assumption to
derive this one and to use the attention
uh instead of wholy kind of using the
observation the other condition uh we
may have some model level approximation
but we again we don't use any
conditional Independence assumption so
which is very good but I say that
mathematically one of the biggest
approximation the conducted in the
attention based deod is this teacher
foring
part by the way there are of course you
know okay if if that is approximation
why not we can repacing this part to be
the predicted
history this is actually fine this may
be probably sometimes better result than
the ground truth however this actually
uh making the training very
slow so if we have a kind of a correct
the answer in the history and then
problem becomes easier so that we can
actually train this model other quickly
this actually benefit of the the using
this approximation teacher foring so
some people actually using you know
until the some point using the teacher
foring and then later that using the the
predicted history and so on which might
be kind of improve the performance and
so on there are lot of techniques are
developed for this kind of areas and so
on but anyway teacher foring is not but
approximation especially this attention
training is very difficult so providing
the kind of ground truths of the history
at a guide is not a bad idea
practically okay so I think uh that's it
from the attention based ASR and I just
want to summarize that uh again
attention based doesn't have any
condition independent assumption and
very beautiful uh by way this is so
beautiful so that I actually started to
use the the attention based data uh
first I kind of found this
method uh but the uh there's couple of
issues like uh the the uh the teacher
foring is one issue and uh also
attention where
especially cross attention is very
flexible uh which is not the appropriate
for the model uh modeling for speech uh
processing speech and so on so that the
uh the other people other method method
like CTC and RN transer is widely used
as an alternative to attention based
ASR okay that this from the attention
based ASR and any question
so okay now move to the another one
CTC um CTC actually has a lot of
explanation I did right especially try
to have a connection with the hmm so
that most of the part is actually review
uh and some of the part is just more
like tips or technical kind of details
about CTC and then I also explain about
the some Advanced CTC techniques
okay so uh this is the review of CTC I
hope people just remember it but I just
want to kind of recap some of them uh we
introduced the plank symbol right so
that we can adust adjust
links and the uh with that we can
actually find the the defined alignment
variable alignment variable it's usually
same length without the input feature
right okay you still remember that right
and then similar to the hmm alignment is
actually the quite other the the many
variations it's actually exponential so
we have to uh the consider the summation
over all alignment right uh however Fe
is very difficult but fortunately we
have a dynamic programming to actually
consider all possible alignment to get
the likelihood or even get the gradient
that is what uh we actually
learned and the I will the uh also I
also we also explained about the how to
uh represent the uh alignment and the
whiches are based on the Tories right so
just remember that you know uh they many
cases uh it can be starting from the
Brank symbol or uh initial symbol and
then reaching to uh the end of the
symbol or blank symbol and then uh we
can
skip the uh the blank symbol but if we
have a conductive uh the the token we
cannot actually skip the Brank symbol so
that we try to distinguish this one is
the same e uh the single e or the
repetition of the E
okay so given that let's discuss about
the this part which is you know to
providing the probability for the the
CTC right and after this one was given
we are using this kind of a manner to
compute the all entire Los and so on and
I didn't really explain about this part
but this is actually very similar to the
encoder in the attention based
approaches or even acoustic modeling
but what it is doing is
just every kind of a time stamp we try
to predict the
token that's
it of course we don't know the kind of
alignment so this part is controlled
when during the training uh with a CTC
spe consider all possible paths during
the inference we just using a beam SE
oring so this part is completely uh the
same as the attention based encod the
encod in the attention based models or
acostic models so this means that we can
just uh repeat uh what we have learned
we can use a neural network we can use
the comos neural network we can use the
BM or we can use the Transformer
conforma Branch for and so on uh the
actually the the the this kind of a
Evolution directly are the affect the
CDC performance as
well after we have this kind of the
encoder the the
representation what we will do is again
we will get a kind of this kind of
probability which means that we using a
soft Marx
right and to do the soft Marx we just
converting this hidden state to the
vocabulary
size plus
one what plus one comes
from Brank yes correct
yes so basically that's it and then we
can actually make the uh the CTC
so it is very actually simple and then
loss function part is a little bit
complicated as you are doing in the uh
the you finished in the the coding
assignment three which is know for the
back but fortunately many of the current
the ne Network Frameworks actually
providing the CTC R so you guys actually
don't have to implement it by yourself
you can just call the the the function
but for this part particular the coding
assignment we want you guys to
understand it so we put the part of the
the forward backward algorithm uh in the
uh as a coding assignment and so on so
basically that's it and then we can
actually get the CTC uh the the uh we
can basically the Train the CTC uh very
easily so the compared with attention
based encod decoder it sounds simple
right we don't have a Closs we don't
have a the decoder we don't have to care
about the auto regressive the generation
we just have an encoder we just put a CT
Z function that's
it okay uh however uh it's actually has
a several tips which can be important
when you guys are working on the the to
project so on so I will explain bit
little bit about it I think uh that I
can you know the skip many of the
explanation here but as you guys may
remember uh CTC actually has some
constraint one of the biggest constraint
is
that input must be longer than the
output so we have a
um
and maybe I can move the this one this
is the kind of a
typical uh the CTC pass and we have a
skip here right like this one we have a
skip in the
sorry we have a skip here but we don't
have a skip like this right we don't
have a skip like this right which means
that
to go up we always have to consume one
frame right this means that if the
output length is longer than CDC than
the input length we actually cannot
reach to the end and in this case
actually we cannot train the CTC model
so this actually important uh the the
the the uh the limitation of the
CTC the uh the input LS must be always
the longer than
output fortunately speech satisfy this
condition what about
TTS TTS actually cannot satisfy this
condition so TTS is not used to p CTC is
not used for T the TTS so often there
are a lot of ways to kind of Faking this
like you know
upsampling the token part and then
making it satisfy with a CTC condition
and then try to use CTC for the the
speech synthesis DTS there are such kind
of techniques exist but generally
no okay and this means that the
if it getting
shorter uh we actually the still we can
find this path but the if getting
shorter and
shorter uh there is a
problem and the tal three and this SE
case uh first other short quit
and maybe you can also open the to
to we can
do yeah please do
the try the both the sh quiz one and the
shter quiz
two shter quiz one is uh the similar to
this case s
e and the shter C two is actually the
one character is changed from e to
a there
um so the answer first
answer
is uh e case right I forgot which one is
no uh actually we cannot
the reach the uh the end of the the
symbol because uh the or the because uh
the uh we cannot uh the the uh the pass
the blank symbol here so we actually
have to go through this one this one and
this
one even character LS is three if we
have a
consective character and then we
actually have to go through the blank
and we actually have to have our
additional uh the the thingss to satisfy
this kind of a condition while if we are
not using the
uh if uh this is not the
consective uh character and then we can
actually skip this so in this cases we
have a pass from this one to this one to
this
one and then actually uh we can reach
the the end of the sentence and then we
can compute the loss so it's not very
simple actually we also have to consider
the the consecutive uh the the the
tokens and so on but generally please
remember that the CTC is not well
defined if the input lenss is uh the
nearly shorter than the uh the output
lenss and this is actually one of the
big uh the
uh uh the tips so I just want to kind of
emphasize it now that the you guys are
actually working on the time project and
so on some of them are working on the
CTC or CTC attention and so on and uh uh
this actually quite often
happens uh when uh we actually using the
uh data spe is not the well
arranged so most of the cases actually
speech is uh the speech input is longer
than output token most of the cases CTC
uh the the condition is satisfied so we
actually
don't care so much about the usual
cases but the if for example you try to
use a new data if you kind of a made a
mistake in the data
preparation if you for example made a
mistake or a little bit kind of a wrong
parameter setting in the down sampling
and so on and then CTC condition is not
satisfied and then what's happening
actually if many of the sentences
doesn't satisfy this kind of a
conditions training becomes very
unstable uh because that we cannot use
the full amount of data we have to use
the data that only satisfying the CTC
condition so this is actually one of the
quite the other frequent other the
questions that we kind of accept are the
the the the your kind of our training is
very unstable and then some cas Cas is
training is not kind of working at all
uh how to deal with that this a very
typical question uh we kind
of we received and then in these cases
please check the output in the input
L and then if uh there are some kind of
issues related CTC related errors mostly
uh by fixing this part you can actually
solve this problems and so
on
okay so this is the the one of the
important tips in
CTC and the another uh the uh remark of
CTC compared with attention based inoda
decoda is that output
dependency so remember that the the
uh the atten based encod decoder we
actually using a condition Independence
we actually don't use condition
Independence assumption at all right
which means that we fully take care of
the dependency of the output
label however CTC is actually are using
the conditional Independence assumption
here and please look at from here to
here for me it's a super big
approximation they actually don't
consider any
history so uh this is actually making
the problem simple but of course in
terms of model it is not great right
because speech has a dependency in the
output token output token sentence has a
dependency right so this actually has a
super big assumption and it actually has
a pros and cons first you know
approximation is not always bad
approximation is important for our
engineer
this becomes our model simple right this
is a b quite big benefit of
CDC and the second part I will explain
later inference actually becom super
fast by using this kind of particular
condition and another part is that we
can combine the language mod
safety this actually doesn't consider
any history right which means that we
actually don't have a langage model
component as I mentioned attention based
enod decoder the language model
component and then if we combine with
the language model it has some kind of a
conflict and then we may need some kind
of regular language model treatment and
so on but CTC doesn't have this so CTC
can actually safely combine the large
langage models and so on without any
kind of the the performance degradation
and so
on it's you know that doesn't hold the
the language model uh it's the sound
like the the
disadvantage but the by combining the
external language model it becomes quite
a powerful but this means that it's not
fly end to end right we using the
additional model and so on so some
people may call is the CTC is not the pr
and to end which is comes from this part
we always need to have some language
model to the make CTC to be working
reasonably but of course this is
approximation this is a big advantage
and the performance is definitely
dropped
unfortunately and compared with the
attention based encoder decod and RN
transer CTC itself without langage model
generally performance is
worse okay so I will also explain about
this inference part
so uh the the CTC is actually uh the
getting the uh inference in a very fast
manner so we CTC by the way very
strictly try to solve the CTC with kind
of considering the uh the uh the CTC
Rule and the language model we need beam
search but actually we can also use the
greedy search is kind of one
approximation but it's very
powerful uh G such the uh remember that
we actually taking the AR
Mar every time St
right and then let's do the CTC and do
the the uh
the uh the good research for this
equations this means that you know that
we first do the kind of the the agmax in
the first time stamp second time stamp
to do the the agmax are the the last
time stamp to do the the
aax however there is no
dependency in the history in the CTC
actually this agmax part can be
independently are the are the
appli and then actually this part is
fully
paralyzed so to take the arax in the
second part we don't have to uh the care
about the result of the P one because it
doesn't depend on that mathematically
okay right since it doesn't depend on
that we can actually even we can change
the order which is fine because it
doesn't depend but this property means
that we can actually even parallelize
the search
part so so this is actually the making
the the search very very first GRE is
search is already you guys think that
it's very fast right because it's just
kind of one time one time to make some
decision instead of beam search and so
on but this one is even faster because
this part is paralyzed so this the
approach is also quite kind of important
in the recoding so due to that the CTC
is still using as a powerful the
techniques uh instead of having a
complicated beam search or the reducing
having also additional the the
computational cost we can actually
parallelize and getting the result very
quickly by the way this nature comes
from the the the strong kind of
conditional Independence assumption we
actually removing the kind of Auto
regressive nature right so this model is
also called non Auto regression model
not only for the CTC all other kind of
model which has a kind of the the weak
dependency or less dependency or no
dependency in the other conditions we
can actually avoid Auto regressive the
generation and we can actually paralize
the decoding part so this kind of
property is no called non Auto
regressive and CTC is one of the very
powerful non Auto regressive model in
speech at
processing okay so uh this is about the
basic of the CDC the part of the the the
the explanation is just reviewing it but
in addition I kind of giving some of the
the tips of the CDC and now I am moving
to a little bit more advanced CTC
technology we still have time right okay
good so that I just want to recap that
CTC has a conditional Independence
assumption
right which making the CTC very
unique however the
question CTC really do not hold any
token dependency in the
model what do you
think mathematically output lbel doesn't
have a dependency right so this means
that the CDC really doesn't hold any
token dependency
Yes actually the hidden state
is quite dependent
right and
uh it is not very
explicitly uh the the uh dependent but
hidden State have some some already
information about the pon or some other
token already right and the neur network
what they are doing is gradually
changing the representation from the
lower layer which is more like a just a
pure acoustic feature having a more kind
of the optimization and then they
they're getting the the hidden state to
be more kind of meaningful
representation and the final one becomes
just a pony so intermediate
representation actually has some P
information already right of course it
is not easy to know fly visualize it but
definitely intermediate representation
already has for like
information and then after the self
attention or blcm or whatever if we have
such kind of dependency the considered
in the model actually this the part
implicitly has other context information
so output label lab the in terms of the
explicit output label or mathematically
CTC doesn't have a
conditional CTC that doesn't have a
label dependency but actually inside the
model uh the this they actually can
somehow hold the the the label
dependency implicitly and then it's not
completely independent this actually
having the turns out that the output has
a quite kind of
consistent across the kind of all frames
and so on so this is actually the the
interesting part of the ne Network
architecture you know mathematically in
the last output form is completely
explicitly independent but actually
internal it has some kind of dependency
by the way this part is of course
boosted after the Transformer so before
the CTC becomes the the Transformer
based implementation bstm or com neur
Network it's actually weak in terms of
getting the kind of the Hidden State
context information but after the
Transformer this actually becomes very
strong and this is one reason that CTC
after Transformer it actually becomes
very powerful so some people had some
kind of a mention that no no CTC is very
weak model we should use the uh the the
attention or we should use the r because
CTC doesn't have a hold the the label
dependency it's not completely true
anymore based on our strong neural
network
inorder is that what we want to do
everything yes okay cool so this is
actually implicit part however there are
recently very cool direction of try to
actually still
implicitly but a little bit more
explicitly in the the the putting the
information about the context I will
explain this kind of technique it's
called intermediate CTC and the self
condition
CTC and the intermediate CTC is actually
putting the CT Heros in the middle and
the final part we basically setting the
same CTC r or may use a different roses
uh depending on the our kind of the the
the design and so on but the important
part of this work is that putting the CT
zos here means that this hidden state is
now quite kind of a similar information
to the ponum right otherwise we cannot
predict H sorry not Tok not Pon token
right otherwise we cannot prct talk
right so without this this can be a more
like the
General the the hidden state but by
putting the loss here uh this becomes
more are the explicitly still not fly
explicit but more explicitly are the
providing the information of the token
here right and the later part is self
attention or BSM whatever which has a
kind of
interactions so this is actually way to
uh the break the the conditional
Independence assumption in CTC
and this is actually also the the
techniques developed in CMU by the way
and the next approach is actually
extension of the this intermed CDC which
is after we predict the uh the after we
have kind this branch and then getting
the CTC to compute the the SE the output
we actually feeding back this
information
here and then just you know adding or
multiplying or concatenated to the
original features and so on but this one
is you know that the actually after the
soft Marx which is almost having a token
information
right by doing that we can add more
explicitly including the the token
information here and then again after
that we have the Transformer self
attention or vstm to consider the
context information so the this part is
actually more explicitly consider the uh
the condition the the label dependency
in CDC so this self condition CTC and
intermediate CTC are actually way to
relaxing the conditional Independence
assumption CTC and actually this improve
the performance of CDC a lot so due to
the kind of a technique of this the
delation of the condition Independence
assumption and the strong encoder comes
from the conformer or Branch for and so
on now that the CTC and RN transor
attention based performance Gap is
getting smaller and
smaller and the last approach a last
section is uh the the uh
combination so uh let's kind of review
CTC and
attention the biggest difference is
there's no other condition here plus
there's a other condition here
right however as I mentioned in
attention part attention are the cross
attention part is too flexible and
sometimes very difficult to control
while CTC is hard alignment so it's
actually the framework itself has a
monotonic alignment so there is no kind
of the the flexibility issue of the
assignment so this is actually one of
the difficulties that I had
based on when I first implemented
attention based encod decoder so
attention based encod decoder cross
attention is very difficult to optimize
and very easily actually having this
kind of a long pattern which is not the
correct uh for the uh the the speech
recogition cases right and then the uh
we actually want to uh the solve this
problem uh and then the there are lot of
other Solutions but the our the the
solutions is actually simple so by the
way this one is also the now they
becomes one of the very famous technique
in the end speech condition and this the
P also is also from
CMU the Su G now she's in the meta and
it is a work actually that the I was
company with s
the intership student uh we actually try
to find some simple solution which is
just kind of
regularize this uh the the hidden state
with
Cy that's it we actually just hope that
this regularization making this part to
Le more like the the the monotonic
alignment and then the the the later
that we just still want wanted to use
attention because attention has a level
dependency better than that but we just
attaching the CT zos and then we using
the mar the objective Mar Tas running of
this kind of a
approaches uh this is by the way not the
perfect solution this is just a
regularization I don't Still Force the
monotonic alignment in the model level
but it was actually working quite well
uh this is actually uh the pure
attention model and the joint CTC
attention
model um if we have a more AO uh maybe
attention can have a better uh the clear
kind of a attention C but uh uh the by
using the CTC uh
attention the the multitask training we
could actually uh the mitigate the issue
and even in the early stage we can get
some kind of a clear attention pattern
we are very excited about this
result and the next actually we try to
think about who the the more kind of are
the the are the useful ways to solve
these
problems please look at this one this
CTC is just using other regularizer
right and then we just discard the
result
which is we saw that it's not very kind
of a
useful uh because CTC itself also doing
the speech
right the attention based enod decod
also they doing the speech recogition so
both are doing the the similar things so
why not we consider to uh that combine
these two information one side is you
know the fly kind of solving the
monotonic alignment issue one side is
are good that considering the uh the the
label dependency right this is a kind of
a decoding approaches we propos which is
the CTC attention joint recording that
is actually combined during the beam
search and it's a little bit Advanced
topic so I don't explain detail but
during the beam search we basically kind
of combine the score of the
CTC and attention and that was almost
perfectly solve the issue because this
side at least this output doesn't have a
the Weir the the the alignment issues so
that we can actually safely get the
result which doesn't have any kind of
alignment issues and so on we have
actually quite a good kind of
improvement at that time uh this is the
attention the model and just the
attaching the CTC R which I explained
before actually say improve the
performance however by combining the it
in the decoding St
in during the beam set we actually got a
quite other large Improvement and so on
and this the big Improvement comes from
the kind of a the regular attention
pattern before combining the score we
often have this kind of pattern that I
mentioned I kind of explained before
right the this actually has a the same
CES happen three times these are wrong
uh alignment pattern and again it
doesn't happen at CTC it would happen in
attention by combining them we can
actually uh the mate issue of this kind
of problem and so on and the same for
the another Buton which is also by the
way quite often happen uh the the beam
sech is stopped before the the reaching
to the end and almost all kind of result
becomes the division
era and this is also kind of clear the
wrong attention uh the pattern which is
the well kind of fixed by using the the
combination of the CTC uh the attention
based
approaches so this the CTC attention is
actually implemented in ESP net so this
is the the very stable in terms of
training which SS to the kind of two
Rosses it's actually FAS and robuster
and the coding result is not broken
based on the other the attentions other
crazy result uh but this is not the only
choice actually as you can see that you
know combining two system right two
architecture it's actually bit
complicated uh and uh the the it's
actually also requires the additional
computation cost for both CDC and
attention right so this is actually not
the the only choice or I say that many
actually people also using a various
solutions for uh the the uh this kind of
the problem and so on but this is
actually quite one of the priding
solution and many of the the the uh the
framework the ASR framework is actually
having this CTC attention architecture
and so on so by the way yeah this is
actually one big remark I think some of
you guys may also touching the the large
language model and so on right it was
not easy to control the lenss right
sometimes you know they kind of over
generate and sometimes it's too short
and then we just using a temperature or
some other kind of hyper parameter to
make the ls and the language model cases
it's more difficult because the lenss
cannot be may not have a kind of the
real kind of a correct lenss but speech
conern cases uh the it's clear right the
the speech and corresponding text so
language should be some kind of range
right so this the uh the approach this
kind of appro AI knowledge is very
important so I'm very sure that you guys
already may have some questions probably
for that if you guys kind of do the
attention based enod decoder you guys
may have this kind of a pattern and then
you know your result is for example the
the uh the the water error rate is over
100 due to the uh the why it happen by
the way water rate becomes over 100
which error will make the
water over 100 ision substitution
division which one will make the water
rate over 100 yes yes insertion and this
is actually very good example it's so
many insertions it's actually the water
becomes over the 100 and so on
this Cas is uh delion is very large
right so uh the our kind of uh the the
the
uh assignment may also have
a uh the the part to check the result
right and then here you actually have a
way to check the number of insertions
and number of
DS so if your result is wrong please
always check them if the number of
insertion is extremely large or
extremely the number of divisions are
extremely large in this cases probably
uh the first model may not be well
trained or your kind of the search uh
the the hyper parameter is wrong so
anyway by checking the result we can
actually understand what error that that
happen happening there very important
remarks and some of you here may
actually have this experience so if you
guys have some the weird result do not
only check the W erator please also
check the breakdown of the how many
substitution error how many insertion
error how many divition error do you
have and also if you the have also the
the the access to the result please also
check the the error butn and so on the
the the ESPN net generally kind of
producing the result which is with this
kind of information how many insertion
how many D and which part of the word is
insertion which part of the the word is
token is deltion substitution so on uh
please check them and then you guys can
see what's happening and then you guys
can find a way to solve this problem and
so
on okay um
we still have 10 minutes okay I can try
to kind of fix finish it uh rest of the
part so uh another approach that I also
want to explain uh with an extension of
the CDC is uh the mask prediction uh
based approaches this is actually uh one
way to solve the
CTC uh without losing the uh benefit of
the non Auto regressive
nature so first the when I introduce the
mask uh dat I also explain about the The
Mask prediction like for example The
Hiding some word and from the the near
the context word to predicting the uh
the uh the the hided uh the hidden uh
the token that is called The Mask
prediction and actually by combining
this the CTC and mask prediction we can
actually uh consider the label
dependency and also can uh avoid uh we
can also maintain the benefit of the non
Auto nature so
that's there are several techniques are
proposed but one of the techniques is
called mask CTC and uh this I will try
to explain a bit more detail so it's
also very interesting Direction so uh
this is a kind of a
conventional uh the encoder
decoder right and then we have output
and so on and now we also studied that
you know CTC can be actually put as an
additional loss
here that's it a kind of the the basic
form of the CTC uh attention
architecture and so on
uh however uh we actually are making uh
this part to be extended by using the
iterative mask prediction based the
decoding and so on I will explain one by
one so first this approach is two pass
approaches we do the kind of two the the
the search but this search is actually
uh the uh the grey suchar and the the no
par search so it's cost is very small so
first pass we just doing the CTC grid
research no we can get the result the
quickly
right and then second PA we feeding this
kind of output to this kind of a special
Transformer decoder and then getting the
result and so on and how they are
defined I will explain about
it so first uh the let's think about CTC
the prediction which as I mentioned it
is that considering the by considering
the conditional Independence assumption
it's actually quite error
problem and then in these cases for
example uh the S and a can be a kind of
wrong uh the uh prediction and so on and
then in these cases we first checking
some kind of confidence which is if we
checking the soft Max activation we can
actually get the confidence if the the
soft Max is very peaky then the uh it is
very confident right and if the Soft
Mark is very kind of uh the the uh the
the wide the tail and then this kind of
prediction is not very confident we
first check this confidence and then
identify that which kind of token is uh
not confident in terms of soft Mark
activation and so on
and then after that we actually feeding
this uh part as a mask we hide them and
then these are kind of more confident
information right and this the masked
information is actually less confident
so by using this confident information
to predict the mask information so he
actually using the many of the NLP
techniques like a b and so on and this
is actually combining this kind of
bbased mas prediction with the other the
CTC
approaches and then fortunately if we
have some kind of a better prediction
like this one is actually turns out
correct but this one is wrong but by
using the context information and the uh
encoder information here uh we may
recover this approaches and then uh
this by the iterative performing this
part we could actually consider to
improve the performance by using this
kind of iteration and so on sounds like
a computationally heavy because this is
having iteration right but don't worry
about that because this part is fly self
attention and also this part is actually
also doesn't
depend output is doesn't depend on each
other so this part is actually no water
regress part form so this is having some
additional iteration but the by using
this kind of architecture entire
framework is still not regressive and de
coding part is not like a beam search it
is fastly predicting the result and so
on so this is a one example of the uh
the The Mask CDC actually the first CTC
result has a lot of
errors but by masking the the
unconfident part and predicting from the
kind of other The Confident information
we can actually iteratively recover the
better performance and finally getting
the uh this part is actually correct uh
this part is correct and this part is
remaining wrong but uh this is actually
another way to break the conditional
Independence assumption by using the
mask language model and so on
okay so this is uh the the the uh the
summary of the CTC so CTC is the most
simple n and ASR uh this is the s to the
conditional Independence assumption but
due to the conditional Independence
assumption it has a pro and cons that we
actually the discussed before and some
people may think that no no CTC is are
old Techni CTC is actually other due to
the conditional Independence assumption
it is not the state of the
other partly I agree but I actually
don't hly agree this one due to the kind
of strong encoder and due to the kind of
a lot of techniques to deling the
condition Independence assumption CTC
performance is actually getting better
and better and also due to the kind of
very nice paration capability in the
decoding the beam search part actually
CTC is still powerfully used or some of
the application CTC is very necessary so
this is actually the summary of the CTC
part and then I will move to the uh the
uh weekly assignment today uh any quick
question about CTC